The biggest bottleneck in healthcare AI
aren't the models. I think it's the data
and it's just not healthcare. I'm
talking about AI in general. Most
organizations, they're not struggling
anymore with building AI, but they're
struggling with using data safely. Data
within healthcare is uniquely hard for,
you know, a few reasons. First, it's
highly sensitive. Second, the data is
fragmented, right? I mean, it sits
across so many places within electronic
health record systems. But what they are
actually going to be doing with that
data and what's the intent behind that
that data that typically is not
understood within our traditional
security systems and gods. Today's
conversation is with Sid Dutta cyber
security veteran who has been a data
protection executive across various
large corporations such as American
Express Worldpay Activision Blizzard
King and product head of voltage data
security at Micro Focus which is now
OpenText. He is now the founder and CEO
of Privaclave AI which is solving some
of the deeprooted challenges in
protecting sensitive data especially now
in the age of AI. Sid's work focuses on
one of the most constrained layers in AI
data flows. While much of the market is
focused on models and algorithms, his
perspective centers on the runtime
visibility, governance and protection
that bakes in privacy and trust by
default and by design. He works on
enabling secure privacy preserving
collaboration, making it possible to
analyze and process sensitive data
within healthcare, financial services,
and other industry sectors across legacy
and AI workflows without exposing it and
impacting it to customer or patient
privacy. That shift has implications not
just for innovation, but for how
institutions think about risk,
partnerships, and accountability. This
conversation focuses on where AI efforts
to where AI efforts stall before they
begin. What is limiting progress today
and what needs to change for healthcare
data to be used safely and effectively
at scale. Sid, I want to start with the
the layer that gets the least amount of
attention. Before we do, just I want to
say thank you for being here and welcome
to the signal room.
Thank you for having me, Chris. AI gets
most of it the focus in healthcare right
now, but a lot of initiatives stall long
before models are ever deployed. Where
do organizations actually hit barriers
when it comes to data? And why is
healthcare data so difficult to access
and collaborate around compared to other
industries?
Oh, that's yeah, it's a loaded uh
question. So going to break it apart a
little bit. Uh but I think that's a
great place to start the conversation,
right? Because honestly the biggest
bottleneck uh in healthcare AI you know
aren't the models right I think it's
it's the data and it's just not
healthare talking about AI in general
most organizations you know they're not
struggling anymore you know with
building uh AI but they're struggling uh
you know with using uh the data safely
and uh comes to healthcare uh data uh
within healthcare is uniquely hard for
you a few reasons right first it's
highly sensitive uh you're dealing with
PHI, you know, protected health
information regulated on and the risk
isn't just financial, you know, it's
patient trust and and safety. So that
makes organizations extremely cautious.
Second, the data is fragmented, right? I
mean, it sits across so many places
within electronic health record systems
or electronic medical record systems,
imaging systems, labs, billing
platforms, you know, all in different
formats, different owners. and often you
know with limited interopery and then uh
the controls typically that are
implemented at these platforms you know
particularly with the fire systems like
epic and suner you know they're they're
very well-maintained as long as the data
is you know sitting within those
platforms but they don't travel with the
data the moment you know data leaves uh
the EHR boundary you know whether it's
going to an AI model a co-pilot
essentially accessing it or an you know
agentic AI framework where an agent you
know goes from being an MCP client who
talks to an MCP server to access EHR as
a tool resource or even for patient
analytics you know sending to a third
party or in a cloud collaboration all
those native protections are gone at
that point right it's kind of a wild
wild west so that's where I think
typically where we would find that the
initiatives will stall because now
security and compliance teams um uh you
know they are concerned about that we
don't really have visibility and and
control uh and we also don't understand
some of the intent Because typically
when it gets to the non-deterministic
aspect of you know AI identities you
know what we call as nonhuman identities
uh that we know who is accessing and
what they are allowed to access but what
they are actually going to be doing with
that data and what's the intent behind
that data that typically is not
understood with you know traditional
security systems and guardrails. So that
kind of leads to you know delays of
projects and and typically you're not
moving past you know pilots and PC's and
compared to other industries you know
healthcare has a much lower tolerance of
risk right so uh but it's still relying
on security models that were designed
for static systems and not dic AI
workflows and that's probably what the
gap is you know between data access and
data protection slowing down
that's an important point you just
mentioned too it was Because healthc
care by definition has never been
static, but we've always measured things
like it is. You know, the pace things
are moving at this point. It it's really
kind of imperative that what you're
talking about, we are bringing that
bringing it to the forefront and having
these conversations and people are
understanding how urgent it is that we
start to think about this differently
because of the fact that pace is what it
is. And it's not static. the practice of
medicine is has always been considered a
practice and unfortunately we keep
discovering new things probably because
we're they're self-imposed in terms of
the the health conditions that seem to
be popping up every so often co 19 and I
think we all heard about SARS but um
that was a whole another level that we'd
never seen before and I I don't think
there's any shortage of those things in
the future and that'll mean epidemics or
pandemics but just new conditions
because of all the crazy things that we
think are improving our lives, whether
it's chemicals or whatever that go into
food processes. But but getting to some
of the the challenges from an
organizational standpoint and when
you're talking about interoperability,
it's always been a complaint that
physicians have had um that I've talked
to, but there's a lot of legitimate
reasons organizations actually need to
collaborate and share data. What are
some of the concerns that you see that
pop up first? Yeah, I think the the
first concern uh I would say that will
pop up is what happens if that data got
exposed, right? So typically when the
collaboration is happening uh there
there is either a data share agreement
um in place in terms of ensuring that
you know as the data essentially is uh
shared with other uh entities uh the
protecting the data kind of lies with
them but that
at the end of the day you know
compliance and security and efficient
privacy is not really laid out on
documentation. and compact right where
there when when the security controls
are not in place and that's where uh
typically the concerns will be that okay
there's one aspect of thou shall protect
my data that I'm sharing or as we are
collaborating on it but the other part
is do I have the runtime and real time
security controls you implemented to
ensure my data you know doesn't
essentially get leaked and then results
in add scenario and then loss of you
know patient trust.
Yeah. And then there's this other aspect
too. You talk about the approvals for
for what what data movement and
collaboration is going to go on. There's
also this movement now for a regulatory
standpoint towards transparency and
explainability which adds a whole
another layer of complexity for the
whole idea about informed consent
because I mean if if you can't speak
plainly about it in in terms of the
non-technical it's going to understand
that it really can't be truly considered
informed. So uh definitely some
additional layers of of challenge on top
of that. Um, that kind of gets more some
of these privacy regulations that we're
hearing about around the transparency.
California, I think, was the first one
that I at least I heard about that was
kind of mandating this explanability and
transparency. But how do these
regulations, institutional risk and
governance structures shake what is
possible? It seems like there's probably
limitation or at least it feels like
there's more than than is comfortable.
Yeah. I mean, I'd love to hear your
perspective because I think there's
constraints. I mean data access
accessibility versus technical
capability those are two different
things. No, that's true because I think
there's there's obviously a lot of the
privacy enhancing technologies and they
they have existed even before you know
AI was was a real concern and then we've
actually you know had tried a lot of
these um you know capabilities
where things like homorphic encryption
things like differential privacy things
like federated learning uh and even
trusted execution environment where we
call as confidential computing or secure
enclaves where technically all data is
you know basically being accessed within
that you know secure enclave. So at the
bottom is that you can you know get the
value from the data without exposing the
data itself. But a lot of cases some of
these have not been you know very
practical or enterprisegrade
um and and not successfully put into
practice. Right? So in in those areas uh
the concerns around usability of the
data or essentially the performance um
um you know for those you know processes
that are operating under those
privacy-enhancing technologies um you
know have been under question. Uh but
there are like other uh methods who have
you know which have proved to be more
effective you know where data
deidentification or or data
desensitization
uh um you know having those data uh
offiscated and persistently you know
protected as they're moving as they're
being stored or being accessed or or
being you know analyzed. So in a lot of
cases those have been proven to be a
much better alternative but each of them
has its own uh effort and engineering
and and complexity and in a lot of cases
uh that you either lack you know the
necessary resources or the funding to
implement uh that and when it becomes an
after the fact it even gets a lot more
uh invasive and complex and expensive.
Uh so then you tend to kind of relax
your controls to uh something that is
very default and very traditional of
platform level you know security data
encryption at rest um right that
potentially you know puts the data at
risk uh but some of these other
techniques have been very hard uh to
implement and that's where I think some
of the the gaps actually reside. Yeah,
there there there's definitely some some
things that are unique, you know, when
you talk about the security and the all
the regulatories and policydriven things
that we have to deal with. Having an
evolving model is very it particularly
with AI, it's it's a whole different
ballgame and what you got approvals for
a month ago if if you don't revisit some
of those things, the the things that you
approved may mean something completely
different very very shortly. And I think
that's one of the the challenges in in
addition to the technology which I I
think why um I have so much respect for
the work that you and your company are
doing because there's so many other
areas that people have to worry about.
This is one they really they they need
some professionals to be paying
attention to it. So the great you know
perfect leap into a concept that I've
heard you use but I really love to
understand a little bit more about it.
uh you've talked about privacy
preserving AI in practical terms what
does that actually mean?
Yeah. So I guess I think I kind of uh
alluded to uh in the previous uh
question that you had. So privacy
preserving AI technically at the core it
means that without exposing the data
itself you can still use the data right
so that's that's where I think some of
these privacy uh enhancing technologies
and stuff like that you know come into
play
is this more in the the identification
process or or tokens or or tokenization
how do you cope with
a lot of it's a combination of of
various you know things and in a lot of
cases either you're picking one versus
the other or sometimes in combination.
So the shift, you know, is that from
moving data to AI to bringing AI to
control data environments. So that's
kind of where it all started that how do
you collaborate um on the data where
that data is actually within a very
secure control environment, right? It's
like the concept of like secure
enclaves, right? So you have everything
operating under that or within that
enclave. So you are bringing your AI and
the processing and into that rather than
take the data and send it to an AI model
you know to do the processing stuff
right because that that's what typically
happens these days is like you know
you're you're actually sending the data
to the models um and you know you know
do inferences and predictions and stuff
and in a lot of cases the guardrails
that you're putting in is at runtime you
know you're analyzing on that data that
you're putting into the AI and and then
basically making sure that the data
which are sensitive enough you know phi
PII you know that technically the model
doesn't really need um but everything
else around that data is what it is
analyzing and inferring on so how do you
at runtime ensure that they are
deidentified sometimes minimization of
the data is also a process that gets
into um um in practice where only expose
what's absolutely necessary and and then
after that anything that needs to be
sent to the AI model, make sure they are
masked or tokenized. Uh because one
thing you'll have to make sure that the
model is able to uh do its job and not
hallucinate because if you send
something and that doesn't make any
sense to uh the model, it obviously will
give you results that are not going to
be favorable for your process. Right? So
it's a very interesting balance that
needs to be struck that what you protect
and how much you know you protect that
it essentially gives you the privacy as
well as it doesn't make the business
process u you know do something that was
not uh you know expected and then of
course you know some of the other
technologies u you know we have used I
alluded to homorphic encryption trusted
execution all that stuff so it it has
been very hard to keep data and bring
the AI to that secure control
environment. So typically the uh the
most frequent and practice models have
been that ensuring how you keep the data
and the context secured um while you're
sending the data to yeah because the
part is a lot of cases these AI models
are operating externally to the
institutions right I mean the hospitals
won't have their own models that are
built in a lot of cases so in that case
you are taking advantage of a a
hyperscaler foundational model that they
are hosting and in that case even though
that's probably by contract or by
segregation or logical tenanting you're
keeping that within that particular
tenant
but at the end of the day you're still
sending it outside your own environment.
Yeah, I think you when we talk about
this that the basically having the
minimum of data access that you need to
actually accomplish something I think is
definitely something it's a challenge
but as you think about what we can do
from a speed and processing standpoint
now with AI models for me I think it you
know that we've talked about this a
little bit so I know that you're this is
one of the areas you're excited about.
So for somebody who's really protecting
privacy and all that, you're also
excited about what's possible and I this
is one of the things I really really
appreciate about what you bring to this
conversation and what your your
leadership means across the industry. So
when these models work, what kinds of
analysis or research become possible
that weren't feasible before? I mean
just positively think back just a couple
years now when we had all of a sudden
had co vaccines. There's a speed
involved there that was never possible
before. But from you, I'd love to hear
what you're thinking about in ter what
what now actually we could consider to
that we couldn't even think about
before.
Oh, I yeah, this this like opportunities
are are so many, right? Even on our side
of the when we actually build products
and and then technically how what the
guardrails that we put in and then take
advantage of these models. You know
there were things that probably would
have uh you know we would have spent a
significant amount of engineering effort
and cycles you know to get the results
uh that currently with these models we
are getting right um now in a in an
enterprise uh sector like healthcare you
know it fundamentally changes what
healthcare can do with that data right I
mean today a lot of high value use cases
are either you know slowed down or never
attempted not because they are
technically hard but uh because they too
risky from a data perspective. So with
privacy preserving approaches uh if they
are put in place and they are put in at
runtime and they are put in uh in a more
contextual and contextaware and
intentalized you know fashion that
you're making certain decisions as data
is moving uh you know to these AI
models. If you are able to successfully
do that, you unlock you know things like
cross institution you know research at
scale right I mean hospitals and
research centers can collaborate on
patient cohorts without actually sharing
raw PHI you know that means you know
better sites faster validation with you
more diverse data sets u sometimes you
know real time clinical decision support
and AI can safely assist physicians
using sensitive patient data in the
moment you know without exposing that
data outside the control bound and then
you know as back office or uh you know
some of the capabilities from a
productivity standpoint where um the you
know uh billing or any other you know
department that they're using you know
AI co-pilots and agents and clinicians
you know administrative staff and they
can interact with the AI system without
worrying that sensitive data is leaking
into external models right I mean like I
was actually talking to someone um who
uh was the founder of a health tech
company and they were solving uh that
how appointment setting you know within
hospitals you know has been a big uh
problem right and try to solve that
through AI you know analyzing you know
historical data in terms of uh patient
visits and appointments and how they are
staffed and across each hour of the day
and across each day of the week versus
each week month and so on so forth years
of data uh that they're leveraging in
order to help patients get you know care
much faster rather than having to wait
for an appointment or doctor to be
available two months down the line.
Right. Right.
So and of course you know secondary use
of data is those are all there like
population health drug drug discovery
operational analytics you know become
you know far more accessible
be used in a desensitized you know
controlled fashion.
Yeah. I mean to me what this is one of
the more exciting things because I I
when I was working in New York uh we had
a a dermatologist who was studying some
pretty rare conditions because of his
practice and when he was able to get his
hands on some deidentified data sets uh
on a larger scale he was actually able
to get enough of a cohort that was
statistically significant enough to come
to some really remarkable revelations in
terms of these rare conditions that he
just didn't have enough context for as
as a clinician to treat. That's just one
example. But it's to me that makes the
work that you guys are doing so much
more important because if we can
actually pull a single thread and
understand the whole uh end to end life
cycle of a patient's record and really
understand what's happening there and we
can put that into a larger, you know,
context. There's just no there's no
limit from from what I could see. I'm
excited about that. There there's some
unfortunate
ways that people think about concepts of
privacy and governance in particular.
What you're talking about doing
something that's a little bit different.
You're talking about using them as an
enabler. It's not a roadblock. So talk
about some of the misconceptions maybe
that people have about privacy
preserving technologies today.
Yeah. Well, I think this is you know has
you know existed for a long long time
right I mean even though my background
has been predominantly financial
services even in those you know sectors
whenever it came to you know
implementing datacentric security or
privacy preserving capabilities it's
this uh notion of losing uh utility of
the data because typically how uh data
is deidentified or desens sensitized is
with you know cryptographic measures um
whether it's encryption uh tokenization
sometimes more one way hash operations
that you anonymize that data it's a kind
of irreversible operation and sometimes
you do basic like masking and redaction
stuff like that right so the all of
these are techniques that we have used
um for decades uh to keep that data
protected um and uh you know preventing
you know misuse of that data but for
legitimate use cases when processes are
running um the uh concern is that I will
lose the ability to use the data I will
uh my business processes are going to
break uh so if you were heavily masking
or distorting data to a point that it's
no longer useful and that used to be you
know true in a lot of cases where very
rudimentary offiscation used to be done
like you know masking like you know make
everything xxx right in that case you
don't you lose the referential integrity
of of a database if there's like the
characters have been replaced with that
or you have blanked out right redacted a
patient social security number credit
card number in that case you know how do
you really operate that on a structured
data set and even with probabilistic
encryption methods um you you actually
had different outputs of cipher text
used to get created after you did the
encryption of the same data even with
the same key because every time you
would generate a different output So you
you are not able to search on that
unless you implement you know certain uh
tag or or like a a static uh some sort
of a hash uh to do the searches on that.
But you know with deterministic
encryption format preserving encryption
tokenization all of these capabilities
have enabled you to offiscate the data
and replace a real data with a token or
a surrogate of it of that and then use
that across your workflows. And so and
then you still enable people to search
on that data to join different tables
you know using that as a primary key
foreign key all of the database
operations that typically gets done and
sometimes you know with additional
uh privacy enhancing uh capabilities you
know there's a belief that these
approaches are too complex and too
academic right federated learning
homorphic encryption you know these are
hard to compromise and and and a lot of
cases that's true right because there
has to be certain very niche use cases
where these you know apply well but they
don't apply broadly frustrated execution
environments you know these like you
know where everything is running under
this encrypted uh you know memory and
it's all in a secure enclave even if you
are able to take a dump of that memory
and there was a memory leak u still
you'll find data encrypted but they they
they operate in very confines of certain
you know uh parameters but the moment
that data leaves you don't have uh homo
uh you know homogeneous ecosystem that
everything stays encrypted as it moves
and then on the other side the data gets
uh you know usable so I think that's
where probably um a lot of concern is
that I want to innovate but security
privacy is bringing me down right I mean
it's a barrier to innovation and in that
case what happens is they they try to
find the guardrails and that's where you
find a lot of the shadow AI happening as
well so security and privacy you know if
they are looked as enabling ers and that
that also has to be proven that they are
indeed enabler and can still do your job
and do more because now these are baked
into the design and by default so you
don't have to really implement something
because that's one of the friction that
uh typically innovators feel right oh
now I have to also implement something
to take care of privacy and security and
that essentially you know drags them
away from the innovation um and and the
actual business impact that they're
trying to make but these are some things
that ask you to kind of operate
automatically at runtime and in that
aspect they don't feel the pain and the
weight of being the ones who have to
implement data privacy and security and
if something just works then they will
not bypass it. So you will have less
amount of shadow AI you know happening
which puts the enterprises more at risk
right yeah shadow AI is a a whole whole
crazy topic that we could probably speak
on for a few days because every
organization's got you know some level
of it probably more than they think
based on I'm sure you've seen the same
kind of thing in your in your work as
well we're definitely in a place where
there's a growing need I think the
pandemic kind of exposed some things in
this regard that there's a need for
collaboration across institutions which
typically has been a little difficult.
Um why you think that's been so
difficult?
Yeah, I think it's it's something that
has been hard to execute um because I
think the data gravity combined you know
with the risk that's associated with it.
So every institution holds sensitive
patient data but the moment data leaves
its boundary you know you lose the
control on it right and once control is
lost uh the accountability doesn't go
away it actually get increased but in
that case you definitely do not have the
direct authority or control on that data
and and ensure safeguards in place right
so typically what happens that you air
on the side of caution Don't move the
data. Right.
Right.
So in that case
probably
yeah you're putting that guard rail
because if I can control the data once
it's shared I might as well not share at
all. Right. And then you have
fragmentation right different HR systems
different data standards different
governance models and if uh two
institutions you know want to
collaborate aligning on how data is
accessed and shared and and protected
becomes a project in itself right
because each of these institutions have
very differing different layers or
levels of maturity when it comes to
their um privacy program or data
governance or data security program and
in that case you you may have a gold
standard on this side but at the moment
the data is shared and they're probably
way less mature in that aspect. So that
that's where some of the challenges are
and
obviously your privacy and regulatory
exposure you know violation of HIPPA uh
can mean heavy penalties and and
long-term you know scrutiny data
breaches are happening every day you
know it's almost unfortunate that we are
kind of getting immune to these news
unless it does something very very
positive you know that uh impacts every
one of us right So and then of course uh
reputational damage all of these things
are there. So even a well-intentioned
collaboration gets slowed down because
of these real concerns given that uh
either the practices or the maturity
across the collaboration are are not at
par or all of them can't align on the
right way of how do we securely share
data? How do we collaborate without
exposing the data? And then uh basically
that's that's a model that you know
technically uh implementation is hard.
See um everybody has the right
intentions but sometimes economically uh
financially and operationally it's
sometimes it becomes a very big
challenge depending on how big you are
and how many you know entities uh you
are collaborating with and how much data
you're topping out
right yeah I think this is this sets up
beautifully one of the things I was
really excited to to get you to talk a
little bit about because this is really
complicated stuff and I've
living around this risk risk stuff for
quite some time myself. But for people
who might not be familiar, how does this
capability that you're using like for
example when I say tokenization, I'm not
sure if people understand what that
means for technology stand or or
methodology standpoint, but there's a
number of different ways that you are
are working with solutioning to be able
to preserve that that privacy within the
infrastructure. Well, this will change
how partnerships could be approached.
But but really the the role that you and
your your your colleagues are playing is
a massive massive advantage for people
if they can start to understand enough
to be comfortable and confident that you
you've got a way for them to actually
accelerate in ways that they never
thought were possible. So how should
that cause us to think differently about
the way we can approach partnerships?
No. Yeah, you're right. Right. I mean I
think this was another conversation that
I was having with uh uh two co-founders
um of another health tech you know
startup that uh they were actually
saying that we don't get the kind of
data from the hospitals that we wish we
did and that that would have enabled our
platforms and our models to actually do
a lot better job at the service that we
are offering to them. And the only
reason that the hospitals were not
sharing a lot of those data because you
know they just didn't have a mechanism
to send something that you know they
could um you know have a control on or
they would not have the concern of that
data getting exposed at after they have
shared right so I think when it comes to
that that it's it's a win-win situation
for like I'm a hospital I'm leveraging a
third party to provide me with a service
and I'm sharing certain data for them to
analyze so that that they can provide
that service but I'm not sharing enough
that they actually would do a superior
job on it and they are constrained
within whatever they are getting. So on
their side they're saying we could do a
lot more if you only sent us you know
some of these other data elements and
hospitals like okay I I can't really
send you that because in that case you
know I'm going to be now risking uh
patient privacy in a lot of cases
because I don't really have a way to do
that. So I think instead of asking you
know how do we securely share data you
know when it comes to the privacy
preserving infrastructure and stuff like
that you shift to like how do we
collaborate without exposing data right
that's a very you know different model
so you enable data to stay sometimes you
know within its home environment and you
have a control policydriven access you
know at runtime and then based on
context uh you you make decisions about
what gets revealed and what doesn't
right so in a lot of cases you bring it
home. Or on the other cases where as you
are sharing um then you you ensure what
gets shared how much you know you need
um and in that case uh what's the
context behind this data sharing because
all data sharing are not the same right
understanding that um you know context
the intent behind that you know sharing
and in that case what data I should be
offiscating I should actually leave it
you know as it is it's a runtime
position
and I think you know products solutions
that are able to make that runtime
decisions are going to enable you know
these partnerships to be more
strengthened right and in that case
these partnerships are entirely based on
these contracts right I mean it's it's
like this is how you know it needs to be
but you don't have any control after the
fact it's kind of more of a legal
document versus an implemented uh
security control so it with with these
you know private privacy preserving
infrastructure as well as these
different uh technologies and solutions.
uh these become less about legal
complexity and and data plans for
agreements but more about controlled
interoperability right and obviously the
impact is huge that you can move on you
know move from months of negotiation and
hesitation to enabling you know joint
research shared analytics and you know
driven insights much faster
right you know you you mentioned
infrastructure I think this is an
important thing too is um there's a ton
of focus on algorithms models
um you know how how many ways that could
go sideways and you know we can tee that
up another area we could talk about for
days but let's talk about the the
infrastructure itself that to support
what you're talking about how important
is the infrastructure to support this
so I think uh
today there's a lot more focus you know
is given on the models right like you
know what model I'm using and the other
part is there are how how good that
model is compared to something else. But
in a real, you know, world deployment,
infrastructure is kind of the difference
between a demo and something that
actually runs in production, right? So
you can you have the best model in the
world, but if your data layer isn't
secure, observable, it's not controlled,
um, and it's not cleaned, right? And the
data hygiene has been biggest problems
because if it's a garbage in and garbage
out thing, right? I mean you put you
know garbage into something it is going
to cough out garbage regardless of you
know what the
unfortunately that's the way it works.
So that's as a without you know having
that data layer you know that is uh you
know hygienic and and it's control it's
secure and and observable right you
simply can't use it at scale
particularly you know when it comes to
healthcare so I think the
underestimation has been done on the a
on the data layer right I mean we have
actually put too much of focus on the
models and stuff um and it's just not
about you know storing or accessing data
anymore. It's understanding you know the
data um like what that data is you know
that is being accessed. What's the
context intent you know behind how it's
being used and then enforce protection
dynamically you know as data flows
across these systems and co-pilots and
and agents. So right existing
infrastructure you know wasn't designed
for that right because we we it was
built for static applications as I was
talking about that deterministic world
right you know the application was
developed in this way this is what it
does these are the data elements it
takes in and this is what it does with
that data this is where it shared shares
or stores and we move to an AI um
nondeterministic world where data is
constantly moving you know being
recombed mind being generated being
interpreted in unpredictable ways and
then autonomous decisions are being made
because you have not pre-wired uh an
agent you know to do a certain thing I
mean the agent is making decisions on
its own so as this big shift you know
has happened uh in that case um we have
our infrastructure was not kept um uh
you know or or couldn't evolve at that
speed so that's where I think uh you
know some of the biggest challenges and
that's where you know Technologically we
can do a lot. We can build powerful
models, process massive data sets and
generate insights in second. But
right
operationally um when it comes to data
privacy, data security is the question
gets asked that can we do this safely
without losing control of our data,
right? And right now that answer in a
lot of cases is uncertain. We we're not
sure. So it's not really the innovation.
It's the confidence and control at the
data layer. you know that organizations
you know do not have and that's where I
think uh we we see that uh the the
challenges um and then how uh AI has
kind of outpaced the way enterprises
have you know built the infrastructure
and and their governance model
yeah I mean that that's obviously a gap
that has existed you know long before AI
just you know the expectations of what
we can do versus what we could actually
implement. Um I think everyone hopes
that there's a that was easy button on a
desk they can hit but
right
that's just not the way it works
unfortunately.
you know we always had this challenges
to your point but I think AI has just
kind of amplified it to uh you know
multiple fold right I mean that's where
I think the biggest pain point is
because we we always tried to catch up
with the digital transformation and has
things you know mature and evolve but
this leap has been very significant
right and that's where we kind of like
find ourselves in a um you know standing
at the bottom of the cliff while you
know something is is way up there
right yeah it's just We're I don't know
just so many different angles to this
stuff and you know we want to talk a
little bit more about you know we don't
dig in on trust a whole lot yet don't I
want to I want to talk about that too
but you know governance trust and
stewardship I I think people are coming
at things with a different level of
understanding of what those things are
trust is another area where we have big
big challenges in almost every area of
life because they of the erosion of
trust in human relationships
But what we're what we need to be able
to figure out in this kind of
environment when we really do have to be
able to share information that's
sensitive across organizations.
Um how do you even go about struct
structuring the governance and and
accountability uh to really enable this
in in the way that we're really doing
our our we're doing our our duty to to
really protect and preserve that
information.
Yeah, I think this is a tough one. Um I
think you know easier said than done
right I mean the the uh evolution has to
be from ownership to shared account to
do with people right and with very clear
boundaries. Now at a minimum you need to
have few of these layers working
together right one that you need to have
a clarity on the policies like everyone
agrees what data can be used for what
purpose under what conditions right and
technical enforcement you know if those
policies are just like documentation
they're enforced in real time as data is
accessed and abused right and a lot of
cases that that is the biggest pain
point and people can write policies and
and you know I've written myself Sanders
and policies and where we found that uh
the technical implementation was the
biggest challenge and then typically
people would pile exceptions to those
polic standards and move on right
because that was like one of the issues.
So, so technical enforcement is like you
just don't have a policy. already showed
an auditor that oh we have a policy in
place but are those implemented that
that is the old deal and and uh next one
is how do you audit and have a
traceability and auditability um you
know aspect right every interaction with
the [clears throat] sensitive data um
that's auged that's visible that's
attributable uh because in a
collaborative environment you know trust
does doesn't come from contracts alone
right it comes from veryable control
uh so that's where I think u you know
some of the things that has to happen uh
as I put the disclaimer easier said than
done uh but those are some of the
foundational ones and it takes you know
quite a bit of time to get get that in
right I think that's a that's an area
where I think probably there's there's a
lot of folks out there they're really
not sure where they stand what are some
of the signals that the leader might be
should be be maybe looking for that
suggest his organization may not be
ready to collaborate safely.
This this is I I come across um you know
a lot of these when I talk to uh you
know security professionals or data
governance professionals you know while
talking about uh you know their risks
and stuff and and you'll be surprised in
a lot of cases they have still a lot of
uh you know I would say reliance or over
reliance on some of the static controls
that have existed you know for decades
and that's what is perceived to be good
enough in the new world, right?
[laughter] So, and it's like you you
come to a point where like is this an
educational moment, you know, for them
that or and you don't want to obviously,
you know, talk about like stuff that
they personally believe in or or this is
something that's their own decision,
right? So, how do you you know have
someone to be a a believer when they
were a non-believer in in some cases,
right? So here the governance is mostly
like role based access control policies
contracts you know there's no runtime
enforcement and particularly even when
data uh is stored or shared u there are
two check boxes that uh you know they
will check and as long as they're able
to demonstrate that with their auditors
and the auditors are fine with that uh
like oh is your data encrypted on rest
is your data encrypted in transit and
basically both of those cases you know
you're having TLS HTTPS you know
operations that are happening which you
know checks that box and anything you
put in in any database or in a cloud uh
storage by default it'll be encrypted at
rest which technically doesn't really do
anything from a security standpoint. Um
so these are some of the things that you
will find if you're like talking to
someone about this and then they are
talking these as their controls then you
know there's a red flag right lack of
visibility into data flows if they can't
clearly answer where sensitive data is
going especially you know with AI
workflows they're not right you know
today tools like DSPM data dis you know
data security posture management they go
and to scan different data stores. So
it's a point in time visibility of data
at rest but the moment the data leaves
you know the systems and where they're
going you know DSPMs and these um uh
tools they can't really tell you. So
your visibility into data flows um if
you don't have that then you know that
you know obviously they're not great and
then I think one of the biggest
challenges I've had when I was a
security practitioner you know being
part of whether it's American Express
world activation blizzard or you know
Micro Focus um the ownership of risk
that's very unclear in a lot of
enterprises and particularly the the
bigger you go grow that's like one of
the things that We struggle with if
there was a database that's like a
shared data m or a data warehouse and a
lot of teams are potentially pumping
data into it and then a lot of teams are
taking advantage of that uh data store
to you know get some information out of
it. It's very hard in a lot of cases to
understand who owns that data store and
basically who owns the risk if that data
store actually got uh you know attacked
and data breaches happened. And in a lot
of cases what happens is there's one guy
on the IT side who manages the server is
basically approving requests for access
to that database and he doesn't even own
the data. But for him the easiest route
is to check on the approve button rather
than decline and go through a series of
conversation why that person requesting
access should need it and whether that's
a legitimate yes or no. So it so
basically people taking the easy way
around basically hey let's me let's let
approve it but he will not be the you
know steward of that data and he would
not own the risk if that you know
database got hacked obviously you know
currently you don't even know you know
who has ownership of that data so that's
that's one of the you know big uh issues
where it comes to um that readiness
right I mean do you have
uh very clear ownership of the risk and
of the assets and then of I think even
the answer to that question may not be
sufficient if the answer is important to
what you just said. It's like it's just
one one person you have a risk.
Yeah. Exactly. I mean and and that
person has like obviously this I was
told that this is a system where
everything comes and and given nobody
actually knew who the data owner was
that that maybe oh given you own the
server you're the IT person you are that
and so that's a very you know
unfortunate thing you know particularly
in in the very complicated and matrixed
organization these are some of the
things that are very common and I think
last but not the least when you you have
the mentality of block first. If the
default approach is to restrict
everything because it's easier, you
know, then enabling it safely, then you
know, it's a clear signal that
infrastructure and the and the paradigm
and the governance model isn't there
yet, you know, for adoption.
Great. I think I think those are
probably some of the ones that that I
think
Yeah, that's a that's a really important
point.
I don't think I've been in a health
system if in 30 years that didn't have
those kind of challenges at some point u
you know as a person who's responsible
to create analytics when someone is
needing data that I can't go get I it it
is a little frustrating because I you
have to be able to explain who why you
can't meet the objective and it it's
really an uncomfortable thing because
organizationally we ought to have our
act together so that we can uh make
those kind of decisions when it's really
meaningful and important to do. So, you
know, if you're to your point, if these
are the things that you're hearing, the
this is something that really needs to
to get some attention, then again, a
very good reason to to have my friend
Sid here on standby, pick up the phone.
But let's talk about the future because
I know we're we're kind of coming up on
time here. As these technologies evolve,
how might the healthcare data ecosystem
change? There'll probably be a shift you
know from institutional centric to a
network ccentric you know healthcare
data ecosystem like I say you know given
that all all the dominoes fall into
place um today you know data is is
siloed every hospital payer research
organization operates within its own
boundaries in the future data will still
you know live in those environments but
it'll be accessible in a controlled
interoperable way across a network. Um
and I instead of asking at that point of
time who owns the data you know we will
start asking you know how can this data
be safely used across the ecosystem. Uh
so I think um when it comes to
collaboration my hunch is that some of
the uh things are are going to be more
common is where we will have a much more
federated and distributed research
network at multiple institutions would
be contributing you know to shared
insights without pooling raw data AI
enabled you know clinical ecosystems
where co-pilots and agents can operate
across systems but obviously with strict
context aware controls what can they
access and reveal
potentially a human in the loop. you
know obviously they'll be there in a lot
of cases particularly for some of the
critical processes and I think uh for
having data clean rooms and secure
collaboration environments for players
you know like pharma you know providers
and players work together on analytics
um trials and you know population health
um and I think uh it's going to be more
context aware and purposedriven data
access model right rather than having
role based access control or attribute
based access control. It's going to
reward intent based uh you know dynamic
access controls on place because
which means basically the same user
could see different data depending on
what they are trying to do right I mean
SID
yes
essentially is you know trying to access
the same data store but given the the
prompt that SID is providing has a very
different intent than the last time we
did in the last time basically we bought
some portion of the data in this the
intent dynamically would be analyzed to
say oh no no no no maybe this is not
something I should be exposing to Sid at
this point even though Sid's role is
already there to access that database so
I think we'll see a lot more of that
getting tightened um and more
contextdriven dynamic runtime decisions
there's there's definitely some some
noise out there when it comes to what
needs to be done for governance and
controls but it seems like there's some
other things that maybe people aren't
aware of. So from from where you where
you stand, what signals are suggesting
to you that the industry might be
entering a new phase like it seems like
it might be.
Yeah, I think we kind of we're probably
getting past that can we use AI mode,
right? I mean it's like it's kind of in
I think it's we're going to be moving
from that to like how do we use it
safely at scale, right? So then um you
know there's going to be a a growing
realization that data protection can be
an afterthought right which
unfortunately in a lot of cases it is
and it it kind of has to be built into
how AI systems operate uh and the only
way that could happen is when it gets in
the runtime mode uh gets into the data
pipelines and the AI pipelines uh
seamlessly and in a very frictionless
manner uh because you you you can't
pre-wire uh these AI agents and and
co-pilots any longer um and which they
don't operate in a you know very well-
definfined scope right they they will
make certain decisions so your
guardrails have to be outside uh and
particularly at that data layer and at
the data pipeline layer and then you'll
probably see some uh you know if you're
seeing some early adopters shift from
blocking the dment to enabling control
data usage which is a
different mindset because our typical uh
approach has been and particularly
healthcare and some of the other
regulatory industry is that uh you're
either in the monitoring mode or in the
blocking mode and and the moment you are
in the blocking mode then obviously
you're stopping innovation and you're
stopping or actually creating business
disruption
um have to shift from there is like how
do I allow you know this uh pipeline and
this process to go through without
exposing you know my data uh in that
case you're essentially enabling control
data usage and control data movement. uh
so that's where I think some of the
signals we will find where we will see
that but we are actually moving on to
that new phase. Yeah, and I it's a it's
definitely not an if or or should we uh
I think the the sudden leap that we all
learned about a month or two ago uh with
regard to what Open AI and Anthropic are
doing uh kind of puts lights a fire and
there's a ticking
ticking clock going down on us where
where we have the opportunity to get
some things right or we're going to be
really far behind and it's going to be
detrimental. Uh so as we kind of close
out if leaders want to unlock the value
of their data responsibly
what are the things they should be
paying attention to right now they may
be overlooking because I think time for
them is of the essence. Yeah, I mean I
don't know if like whether there is one
thing right. I mean that's that's one of
the challenges of security leaders or or
data leaders u in institutions like
healthcare. Um but if they want to
unlock the value of their data
responsibly, I think right now they
would probably want to focus on like
stop thinking about the data access and
the data protection as separate
problems, right? We have been you know
operating in in that model for a long
time and there's a data governance
aspect of you know what data we have and
who has access to it and then the
protection essentially doesn't come with
that has not been part of that in a lot
of cases you know these teams are
probably working together or sometimes
it's under the same leadership in a lot
of most cases they are not so and by
data protection we are again in that
blocking mode so sometimes you know this
party will think the other party as an
adversary rather than you know partners
and that that we should be working
together. So that separation is exactly
I think what you know slowing
organizations down and most teams are
still oper in a model where one side is
trying to enable access and innovation
other side is trying to restrict and
reduce risk to it right and then that
creates the friction and as friction is
created then you have the bypasses
happening right and in that case you're
introduce inadvertently introducing more
risk in the enterprise so what's often
often you know overlooked is the need
for this unified runtime time approach
where access and production happen
together in real time and based on
context and intent. uh so I think these
these functions and and uh the
approaches have to kind of so uh that's
that's what I would see as uh you know
one of the very important things and the
other thing is you know basically like
don't overindex you know on models the
real differentiator won't be which model
you're using but it it is how
confidently you can use your data with
that model right because at the end of
the day
the models are you know fed with data
And then models deal with data and then
that that's what you know they create
outcomes based on the data. And it
basically means that you know if you're
able to confidently use your data with
that model comes down to you know
visibility control and ability to
enforce policies dynamically as data
moves right so that that's what you know
will be required uh to boost that
confidence regardless of what model I
chose. I I can use my data in that
model. Yeah. And you know, as we're
wrapping up, I I just want to encourage
through the listeners. We're we're
definitely in a period of time where we
want to find a way to be able to enable
uh the data to be used in in a
responsible manner. And this is I'm
going to say something that might be a
little controversial, but I'm in part of
the healthcare provider sector for a for
a larger part of my life. Um, we often
tend to be a little ambitious and think
that we're prepared to just build things
on our own. Things have gotten so
ridiculously specialized and there's so
much uh time and energy being spent on
both sides of an equation. One is trying
to advance the capability and stay ahead
of those who are trying to penetrate it
and do nefarious things. The escalation
is constant there. This is not something
you want to be a hobbyist to try to
solve. Not We you don't want to be a
well-meaning person if just try thinking
you really can do this. You really need
solid partners. And this is where
sitting in in the team at private
committed from my perspective. And I
just want to encourage all of you. You
know, I'm going to have a whole bunch of
information for you in the show notes.
Uh but please you take take the
opportunity to look at this if you're in
a place where you're you're feeling that
pressure. You've got to be able to
enable responsible use. um this is a
conversation that that you want to
engage in. So please make sure that that
you take a look and and reach out to to
Sid and his team because you you really
have to have solid partners and if this
is not a scenario where you can have 25
different small players that are use
case driven. This is a foundational
aspect that he's been talking about.
So Fed said, I I really just appreciate
you taking the time and I think the the
takeaways for me are uh many uh but you
know you talked about contextual
awareness which really was an important
thing as as well and you know what I
hear from you is not stop and roadblock.
It's let me help you accelerate. Let me
help you do it in a way that's going to
protect people and protect their
privacy. Um I I love that. um you know,
as we wrap before I just close it out,
uh anything that that you're thinking
about over the next, you know, year or
so, um that could be a real gamecher
that you've got your eye on. I I'm this
is one I'm always curious about because
you you see things from a different lens
because you're you're really dealing
with things under the under the covers
that most of us don't even understand.
Yeah. Um I would say it's just to kind
of underscore the point I was talking
about. I think at the end of the day,
you know, AI doesn't create value from
models and it creates value from data.
Whoever can use data safely in real time
will actually win and in that case we'll
have to pivot from
the perimeterbased
type of controls trying to be you know
build bigger walls around the protect
surface. is to focus on the data itself,
right? And that by data focusing on the
data itself is essentially not just from
a security standpoint but from from its
hygiene standpoint as well. So I think a
lot more focus will be around the data
rather than the systems that are storing
the data and their native controls and
the network you know where this systems
actually reside. uh so I think you know
at the end of the day it will um decide
that whoever is actually doing a better
job actually winning or and in a lot of
cases actually succeeding in in every
sector they they actually have the the
most cleansed data and also they're
using AI you know very effectively with
um you know maximizing their usage or or
introduction ction of those data into
those AI models because they have taken
the privacy and the security uh you know
aspect well given that they they can
confidently push a lot more then they
are able to now uh so I think that
that's what probably my closing uh
thought would be so because you can we
can't see these two things differently
it all has to come together if adoption
and the value that we want to generate
out of AI is something that in all of
our you know success measures and KPIs
will be based on.
Well, I I didn't hear you say that, you
know, an algorithm or AI are going to be
the superstar.
So, I think I I think that that that's
heartening for a lot of folks because,
you know, there's a lot of different
fears that are out there, but you're
you're really making me feel a lot
better. So, I appreciate that.
Yeah, of course. is there's too many
debates and too many um you know schools
of thought on that and AGI of course
those are all you know great topics of
here but yeah of course you know uh my
my focus has been you know pretty
grounded at this point to fix the
fundamentals uh which has been broken
for for a long long time and you can't
expect you know different results by
doing the same things
exactly there there's a term that we
call people like that But I I think I'll
just leave that. I think people know
what is. But Sid, thank you so much for
for coming on the show. This has been a
fascinating conversation for me. I've
learned a lot and I'm excited for for
people to be able to to hear from you
and looking forward to continuing to
follow your successes. So I'm quite
impressed with what I've seen so far.
We've only met just a few months ago. So
um I I really I can't thank you enough.
This has been fantastic.
Thank you. Yeah. I mean it was a it was
a great uh opportunity for me to come to
your uh you know session and and then
have have this dialogue. So really
enjoyed the time and uh uh looking
forward uh you know for for more
collaboration opportunities and uh uh
you know and same thing you know we'll
have to see how this whole space plays
out right over the next uh you know
few years I guess.
Thank you.
That's it for this episode of the signal
room. If today's conversation sparked
something in you, an idea, a challenge,
or a perspective worth amplifying, I'd
love to hear from you. Message me on
LinkedIn or visit cigarroompodcast.com
to explore being a guest on an upcoming
episode. Until next time, stay tuned,
stay curious, and stay human.